Hi and welcome back.
In this course, you've learned
about object recognition,
where the goal is
to input a picture
and figure out what
is in the picture,
such as is this a cat or not.
You've learned about
object detection,
where the goal is to further put
a bounding box around
the object is found.
In this video, you
learn about a set
of algorithms that's even
one step more sophisticated,
which is semantic segmentation,
where the goal is to draw
a careful outline around
the object that is
detected so that you
know exactly which
pixels belong to the object
and which pixels don't.
This type of algorithm,
semantic segmentation
is useful for
many commercial
applications as well
today. Let's dive in.
What is semantic segmentation?
Let's say you're building a
self-driving car and you see
an input image like this and
you'd like to detect the
position of the other cars.
If you use an object
detection algorithm,
the goal may be to draw
bounding boxes like these
around the other vehicles.
This might be good enough
for self-driving car,
but if you want your
learning algorithm to figure
out what is every single
pixel in this image,
then you may use
a semantic segmentation algorithm
whose goal is to output this.
Where, for example,
rather than detecting
the road and trying to draw
a bounding box around the roads,
which isn't going
to be that useful,
with semantic segmentation
the algorithm attempts to
label every single pixel
as is this drivable roads or not,
indicated by the
dark green there.
One of the uses of
semantic segmentation
is that it is used by some
self-driving car teams to
figure out exactly
which pixels are
safe to drive over because they
represent a drivable surface.
Let's look at some
other applications.
These are a couple of images from
research papers by Novikov
et al and by Dong et al.
In medical imaging,
given a chest X-ray,
you may want to diagnose
if someone has a
certain condition,
but what may be even
more helpful to doctors,
is if you can segment
out in the image,
exactly which pixels correspond
to certain parts of
the patient's anatomy.
In the image on the left,
the lungs, the heart,
and the clavicle, so
the collarbones are segmented
out using different colors.
This segmentation can make it
easier to spot
irregularities and diagnose
serious diseases and also help
surgeons with planning
out surgeries.
In this example,
a brain MRI scan is used
for brain tumor detection.
Manually segmenting
out this tumor
is very time-consuming
and laborious,
but if a learning
algorithm can segment
out the tumor automatically; this
saves radiologists a lot
of time and this is
a useful input as well
for surgical planning.
The algorithm used to generate
this result is an
algorithm called unit,
which you'll learn about in
the remainder of this video.
Let's dig into what semantic
segmentation actually does.
For the sake of simplicity,
let's use the example of
segmenting out a car
from some background.
Let's say for now that
the only thing you care
about is segmenting out
the car in this image.
In that case, you may decide
to have two cause labels.
One for a car and
zero for not car.
In this case, the job of
the segmentation algorithm of
the unit algorithm
will be to output,
either one or zero for every
single pixel in this image,
where a pixel should
be labeled one,
if it is part of
the car and label
zero if it's not part of the car.
Alternatively, if you want
to segment this image,
looking more finely
you may decide
that you want to
label the car one.
Maybe you also want to know
where the buildings are.
In which case you would
have a second class,
class two the building and then
finally the ground or the roads,
class three, in which case the
job the learning algorithm
would be to label every
pixel as follows instead.
Taking the per-pixel labels
and shifting it to the right,
this is the output
that we would like to train
a unit table to give.
This is a lot of outputs,
instead of just giving
a single class label or
maybe a class label and
coordinates needed to
specify bounding box
the neural network
unit in this case,
has to generate a whole
matrix of labels.
What's the right neural network
architecture to do that?
Let's start with the
object recognition
neural network
architecture that you're
familiar with and let's
figure how to modify
this in order to make
this new network output,
a whole matrix of class labels.
Here's a familiar
convolutional neural
network architecture,
where you input an image
which is fed forward
through multiple layers in order
to generate a class label y hat.
In order to change
this architecture into
a semantic segmentation
architecture,
let's get rid of the
last few layers and
one key step of semantic
segmentation is that,
whereas the dimensions
of the image have
been generally getting smaller
as we go from left to right,
it now needs to get bigger
so they can gradually
blow it back up to
a full-size image,
which is a size you
want for the output.
Specifically,
this is what a unit
architecture looks like.
As we go deeper into the unit,
the height and width will go back
up while the number of
channels will decrease
so the unit architecture
looks like this until
eventually, you get your
segmentation map of the cat.
One operation we have not yet
covered is what does
this look like?
To make the image bigger.
To explain how that works,
you have to know how to
implement a transpose
convolution.
That's semantic
segmentation, a very
useful algorithm for many
computer vision applications
where the key idea is you have to
take every single pixel and
label every single pixel
individually with the
appropriate class label.
As you've seen in this video,
a key step to do that is
to take a small set of
activations and to blow it
up to a bigger set
of activations.
In order to do that,
you have to implement something
called the transpose convolution,
which is important
operation that is used
multiple times in the
unit architecture.
Let's go on to the next
video where you learn
about the transpose convolution.
I'll see you in the next video.